chemotherapy is one of the most common
treatments for cancer
how effective exactly is it for
improving survival and quality of life
this video and the next will answer
those questions
[Music]
over the next few decades the number of
new cancer cases will continue
to skyrocket are we winning the war on
cancer
sadly in general no
this despite the introduction of
hundreds of new anti-cancer drugs the
war on cancer has been likened to the
war on terror
no matter how many drone strikes you do
it's nearly impossible to kill all the
bad guys and no matter how precise the
bombing one must always consider the
collateral damage
the toxicity from cancer therapy can be
debilitating and not just health-wise
there's also the financial toxicity
patented anti-cancer drugs are priced
at up to nearly a thousand dollars a day
even with health insurance the average
cost of patients for you know stage four
breast cancer for example can run 190
it's bad enough to be fighting for your
life without bankrupting your family at
the same time a problem still common to
this day
who can forget the apocryphal story of
walter white working two jobs with
health insurance and still
could not afford the cancer care now not
everyone is willing to start their own
meth lab but many are willing to go for
broke a large proportion of cancer
patients reported their willingness to
declare bankruptcy
or sell their homes to pay for treatment
i mean look i mean aren't the high
prices justified if new and innovative
treatments offer significant benefits to
patients
but you may be shocked to find out
that many fda approved cancer drugs may
lack
clinical benefit
well then how did they become fda
approved
most approvals of cancer drugs are based
on flimsy or untested surrogate
endpoints and post-marketing studies
rarely validate the efficacy and safety
of these drugs on patient-centered
endpoints let me explain what that means
new chemo drugs are increasingly
approved just based on so-called
surrogate endpoints which means
instead of looking at what we really
care about survival
or quality of life they approve drugs
based on things like response rate
tumor shrinkage
but who cares if a tumor shrinks if it
doesn't actually extend your quantity or
quality of life right
it's kind of counterintuitive but just
seeing a tumor shrink on a ct scan or an
mri is not necessarily correlated with
improvements in survival or symptoms in
fact most studies that have actually
followed people out found low
correlations with survival the most
recent comprehensive analysis found 90
percent of studies of such validation
trials found little correlation with
overall survival
of 36 new chemo drugs approved by the
fda based on these kind of surrogate
endpoints once they were actually put to
the test in the real world only one in
seven
was actually shown
to extend life and half explicitly
flopped and the rest remain untested
revealing that most cancer drug
approvals have not been shown to or do
not improve clinically relevant
endpoints
exorbitant drug prices are bad enough
for treatments that work
but charging vulnerable patients for
drugs without evidence that they
actually improve patient survival and
quality of life is
unconscionable
why doesn't the fda require proof that
chemo drugs actually benefit patients
before approving them
drug companies say that requiring
randomized controlled trials with
meaningful measures would take too long
but the study time reduction using
surrogate endpoints rather than overall
survival is estimated at just
11 months so instead of it taking 7.3
years to come to market on average it
would take 8.2 years yes look we want to
get these drugs out as soon as possible
but only if they're actually gonna help
people do cancer drugs improve survival
or quality of life you
don't need to know according to our
broken regulatory system and things
aren't much better over in europe a
systematic evaluation of chemo drug
approval showed that most enter the
market without evidence of benefit on
survival their quality of life and even
years later there was still no
conclusive evidence that these drugs
offered any benefit and when they did
the gains were often marginal that's why
you see editorials in the journal the
national cancer institute referencing
hans christian andersen the author of
the tale of the emperor's new clothes
the studies all converge on a singular
conclusion only a minority of new cancer
drugs approved by u.s and european
regulatory authorities in recent years
deliver clinically meaningful benefits
to patients
in fact some cancer-related deaths may
be hastened or even caused by the toxic
effects of chemotherapy rather than the
cancer itself based on review of tens of
thousands of cancer patients in as many
as 27 percent of cases the cancer
treatment itself caused or hastened
death okay but it might be worth that
risk if the potential benefit is large
enough
and that's the subject of my next video
how much does chemotherapy improve
survival
[Music]
you